<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<channel>
		<title></title>
		<description>My Homepage</description>
		<link>/</link>
		<atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		
			<item>
				<title>The Pauli Vector and Lie Groups - Part 1</title>
				<description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is part one of two in a series of posts where I elaborate on Pauli matrices, the Pauli vector, Lie groups, and Lie algebras.  I have found that most resources on the subjects of Lie groups and Lie algebras present the material in an overly formal way, using notation that masks the simplicity of these concepts. Learning about Lie algebras and Lie groups is much easier if one first develops an intuition about what is actually happening, and then later dives into complicated notation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will start our discussion with the properties of the Pauli matrices and the Pauli vector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-pauli-z-matrix&quot;&gt;The Pauli Z Matrix&lt;/h3&gt;

\[\begin{equation}
\sigma_z =
\begin{bmatrix}
1 &amp;amp; 0 \\[0.1cm]
0 &amp;amp; -1
\end{bmatrix}
\end{equation}\]

&lt;h3 id=&quot;eigenvectors-and-eigenvalues&quot;&gt;Eigenvectors and Eigenvalues&lt;/h3&gt;

\[\begin{equation}
\begin{bmatrix}
1 &amp;amp; 0 \\[0.1cm]
0 &amp;amp; -1
\end{bmatrix}
\begin{bmatrix}
x \\[0.1cm]
y
\end{bmatrix}
=
\lambda
\begin{bmatrix}
x \\[0.1cm]
y
\end{bmatrix}
\end{equation}\]

\[\begin{equation}
\begin{bmatrix}
1 - \lambda &amp;amp; 0 \\[0.1cm]
0 &amp;amp; -1 - \lambda
\end{bmatrix}
\begin{bmatrix}
x \\[0.1cm]
y
\end{bmatrix}
=
0
\end{equation}\]

\[\begin{equation}
det
\begin{bmatrix}
1 - \lambda &amp;amp; 0 \\[0.1cm]
0 &amp;amp; -1 - \lambda
\end{bmatrix}
=
0
\end{equation}\]

\[\begin{equation}
(1 - \lambda)(-1 - \lambda) = 0
\end{equation}\]

\[\begin{equation}
\lambda = \pm 1
\end{equation}\]

\[\begin{equation}
\begin{bmatrix}
1 &amp;amp; 0 \\[0.1cm]
0 &amp;amp; -1
\end{bmatrix}
\begin{bmatrix}
x \\[0.1cm]
y
\end{bmatrix}
=
(+1)
\begin{bmatrix}
x \\[0.1cm]
y
\end{bmatrix}
\end{equation}\]

\[\begin{equation}
\begin{bmatrix}
x \\[0.1cm]
y
\end{bmatrix}
=
\begin{bmatrix}
1 \\[0.1cm]
0
\end{bmatrix}
\end{equation}\]

\[\begin{equation}
\begin{bmatrix}
1 &amp;amp; 0 \\[0.1cm]
0 &amp;amp; -1
\end{bmatrix}
\begin{bmatrix}
x \\[0.1cm]
y
\end{bmatrix}
=
(-1)
\begin{bmatrix}
x \\[0.1cm]
y
\end{bmatrix}
\end{equation}\]

\[\begin{equation}
\begin{bmatrix}
x \\[0.1cm]
y
\end{bmatrix}
=
\begin{bmatrix}
0 \\[0.1cm]
1
\end{bmatrix}
\end{equation}\]

&lt;h3 id=&quot;perturbation-theory&quot;&gt;Perturbation Theory&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;final-thoughts&quot;&gt;Final Thoughts&lt;/h3&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 16 Nov 2020 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
				<link>/math%20methods/quantum%20field%20theory/2020/11/16/perturbation-theory-and-the-pauli-z-matrix.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">/math%20methods/quantum%20field%20theory/2020/11/16/perturbation-theory-and-the-pauli-z-matrix.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Learner Centered, Performance Based</title>
				<description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;telling-aint-training&quot;&gt;Telling Ain’t Training&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Telling Ain’t Training is a book that focuses on some effective techniques that can be used when teaching adult learners. It covers a wealth of topics, touching on cognitive psychology, the philosophy of knowledge, lesson planning, and effective assessment (among many others). The authors immediately stress their overarching philosophy of training from chapter one - learner centered, performance based. They argue that effective instruction must have these two qualities. Otherwise, students will not leave the lesson with the content that you intend for them to absorb.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the surface, the idea of learner centered and performance based instruction seems pretty reasonable (perhaps even obvious). However, the devil is in the details. How do you build a learner centered lesson for a class of students? How do you effectively assess performance when everybody starts at different skill levels? Moreover, how can we do this in an online environment - one where you do not get any face-to-face interaction with the people you are tryinig to teach?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many researchers and educators are hard at work trying to answer these questions. I would love to offer some ideas that I am going to try out on Cupcake Physics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;learner-centered&quot;&gt;Learner Centered&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learner centered instruction means that the lesson at hand should be tailored to the knowledge and skills of the learner. This is not a new concept; educators have applied models like the Zone of Proximal Development to their lesson planning strategies for decades. However, I wanted to think about how I can implement learner-centered lessons to Cupcake Physics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;keep-the-lessons-small&quot;&gt;Keep the Lessons Small&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It can be difficult to pay attention to a long lecture when you are sitting in a classroom. It can be near impossible to stay interested in the same lecture if it is recorded and played back on a computer. Unfortunately, there are too many distractions that can tear you away from a lesson online - even I find myself drifting away from online physics lectures when I am sitting at a computer, and I have spent a good part of my life focused on the subject! Thus, one of the ways that we keep the lesson learner-centered is to respect the fact that the online learning environment is fundamentally different than that of a classroom. Instruction must be focused and relevant in order to keep the learner interested when it is so easy to find another source online.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;do-less&quot;&gt;Do Less&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This one seems a bit weird at first glance. In an era when we are being bombarded by a constant stream of information, it seems reasonable that we need to do more to keep up. However, learning takes place not just in the classroom, not just on Cupcake Physics, but during the quiet moments when we have a change to reflect on what we have already done. As I develop content on the website, I am going to try to find ways to slow down the pace of learning. The point of this is to encourage the learner to reflect on what has already been done. Self-reflection is one of the strategies that can be used to work towards a truly learner-centered curriculum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;performance-based&quot;&gt;Performance Based&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Performance based instruction means that we want students to be able to apply the knowledge that they have learned from our training. The authors describe this as “being able to act and to achieve worthwhile, verifiable results” (Stolovitch 14). As always, easier said than done. A worthwhile result to a student (i.e. get an A on a test) might not match up directly with a worthwhile result from an instructor (i.e. develop knowledge about fundamental physics). A verifiable result to a student (i.e. get all of the questions on the homework correct) might not match up with the ideas of the instructor (i.e. parse a context-specific physics problem and come up with a best solution where there is no one correct answer). How might we measure performance on Cupcake Physics in order to maximize learning?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;constantly-collect-user-input&quot;&gt;Constantly Collect User Input&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Creating small chunks of instruction is only part of the story. Watching ten short videos back-to-back is not that different from watching one long one. There needs to be user input between each of those lessons to ensure that the lesson is still calibrated to the user’s skill level. This input can serve additional purposes. It might be a gateway to ensure that the student understands the preceding section before moving onto the next one. It might be a crossroad where the lesson goes in different directions, depending on the previous answer. Engagement is not a direct indicator of a learner-centered lesson, but it does imply that the lesson is within the skillset of the student.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;keep-the-feedback-cycle-tight&quot;&gt;Keep the Feedback Cycle Tight&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last but not least, the idea of tight feedback loops ties all of these ideas together. A tight feedback loop will (ideally) keep a student engaged in the lesson at hand because he or she will receive constant feedback on how much progress has been made. Additionally, it will give the program an opportunity to pivot and offer a new piece of content based on the answers given before. The classic idea of “questions at the end of the chapter” is not engaging in an online environment, nor does it does assess performance in an effective way. In a world where the answers to questions can be looked up on a whim, end of lesson questions no longer provide accurate feedback on the skillset of a student.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;closing-thoughts&quot;&gt;Closing Thoughts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a lot more to unpack in this book - far more than can be covered in a single blog post. As I develop content for the site over the next few weeks, I would love to continue exploring some of the lessons that I have taken away from this read. If you get a chance, please visit &lt;a href=&quot;https://cupcakephysics.com&quot;&gt;Cupcake Physics&lt;/a&gt; to try out the site. Until next time!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;works-cited&quot;&gt;Works Cited&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stolovitch, Harold D. Telling Ain’t Training: Updated, Expanded, Enhanced. 2nd ed., Association for Talent Development, 2011&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Wed, 20 Mar 2019 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>/cupcake%20physics/2019/03/20/learner-centered-performance-based.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">/cupcake%20physics/2019/03/20/learner-centered-performance-based.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>The New Cupcake Physics Site</title>
				<description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;it-has-been-awhile&quot;&gt;It Has Been Awhile!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hello again everyone - it has been awhile since my last post. Over the past couple of years, I have been working on Cupcake Physics in my spare time. Cupcake Physics is a website that aims to help students practice physics concepts using customizable quizzes and focused feedback. At this point in time I think the site is ready for an initial release. The important infrastructure is in place and there is a small amount of content that has been developed for the site. However, development is by no means over! I hope to keep evolving the site with new content and features that help students learn physics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Starting today, I will try to write blog posts more consistently and give updates on the new content and features that are being developed for Cupcake Physics. I aim to write one post every two weeks - hopefully announcing it publicly will help keep me motivated! My goal is to create a website that is an excellent resource for those who want to learn physics, but need a different method of instruction than a traditional textbook or lectures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your feedback is always appreciated. Please visit &lt;a href=&quot;https://cupcakephysics.com&quot;&gt;Cupcake Physics&lt;/a&gt; to try the site out. Please send any suggestions for features or content to cyrus.vandrevala@cupcakephysics.com.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 04 Mar 2019 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
				<link>/cupcake%20physics/2019/03/04/the-new-cupcake-physics-site.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">/cupcake%20physics/2019/03/04/the-new-cupcake-physics-site.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>The Tech Stack</title>
				<description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;tech-stack&quot;&gt;Tech Stack&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the past few weeks, I have been working hard to develop the groundwork for the Cupcake Physics site. Although I have had experience developing web apps in the past, this is the first time that I have coordinated all of the parts of a full stack app at one time; I have to think about everything from developing the app to managing deployment to monitoring the status of the servers (and much more). It has been challenging to learn about all of the details of managing an application, and I am sure I will learn plenty more in the future!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to write a blog post that outlines some of the progress that I have made in the past few weeks. I have experimented with a variety of technologies and written a number of toy applications in preparation for my actual project. This is a good time to reflect on some of my experiences. At the very least, this post will help me organize some of my thoughts for future development. Ideally, this reflection might help other developers in their own work. Instead of talking about every detail of my experimentation, I will dive into three different technologies in order to make sure that this post does not become a novel!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-frontend---elm&quot;&gt;The Frontend - Elm&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have experience coding the backends of a variety of applications at my current job and during my research. These apps range from legacy enterprise systems to more modern APIs and use a variety of languages - Java, PHP, Ruby, etc. I am generally comfortable with backend development and enjoy the challenge of implementing business logic in an elegant way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, frontend development has frustrated me in the past. Although I do have a fair amount of experience in this area, I have found the act of writing code for the frontend quite tedious. Javascript libraries and frameworks do help make the experience better, but I feel like I can never trust that browsers will do what I want them to do. No matter how many tests I write or no matter how simple I make my functions, I do not have a high degree of confidence in the code that is shipped out to the user’s browser. There is too much variability in everything from the version of the browser to the device on which the page is viewed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I heard about the &lt;a href=&quot;http://elm-lang.org/&quot;&gt;Elm language&lt;/a&gt; from a co-worker and grew quite curious about it. It is frontend development as I have never experienced - I have never used a statically typed, functional langage (let alone one on the frontend!). After a few tutorials, I fell in love with the language. After writing some well-tested Elm code, I am confident that it does what I expect it to do. As an added bonus, Elm is remarkably similar to Elixir (see below), so the frontend and backend feel very similar - even though they are written in two different languages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-backend---elixirphoenix&quot;&gt;The Backend - Elixir/Phoenix&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://rubyonrails.org/&quot;&gt;Ruby on Rails&lt;/a&gt; was my original choice for the backend of Cupcake Physics. I have enjoyed working with the framework in the past due to the fact that I can develop code very quickly and iterate efficiently. However, I have found issue with some aspects of the framework (e.g. it has a tendency to produce monolithic apps, it couples data persistence very tightly to your business logic, etc.). Since the functional style of programming drew me to the Elm language, I decided to try something new for the backend as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had some experience writing Elixir apps before coming into this project. My experience with Elixir and Rails made the Phoenix framework seem very natural to me. Phoenix addresses many of the concerns that I had about the Rails framework, and it uses powerful elements of the Elixir language (like pattern matching) to create very simple and readable code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;infrastructure---ansible&quot;&gt;Infrastructure - Ansible&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few weeks ago, I had little experience with the operations side of running an app. Thus, a large amount of my time was spent learning how to run and monitor an app. I tried out a few different technologies during the past few weeks such as Chef and Puppet. However, I found that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ansible.com/&quot;&gt;Ansible&lt;/a&gt; to have the right mixture of ease of use and power for IT automation. I especially like the fact that Ansible uses simple Yaml files rather than a domain speicific language to specify and run tasks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;final-thoughts&quot;&gt;Final Thoughts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These past few weeks have been a great learning experience for me. I know I will definitely have to keep learning about these technologies (and others) as I build this app.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until next time!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Tue, 05 Sep 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>/cupcake%20physics/2017/09/05/the-tech-stack.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">/cupcake%20physics/2017/09/05/the-tech-stack.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Restructuring the Site</title>
				<description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;my-plans&quot;&gt;My Plans&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These past few months have been a whirlwind as I finished up my thesis and ramped up at my new job. All the while I have been eager for the day when I can return to regular updates on this site. The silver lining to this story is that the time off gave me a chance to brainstorm some new ideas for Cupcake Physics and its future directions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Up until now, I have been writing blog posts that outline a proof or solution to a specific problem. These posts are certainly useful, but I want really dive into physics education; my goal is to provide students and informal learners some tools that they can use to grasp difficult concepts in all levels of physics. Over the next few months, you will see a few changes on this site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will separate the physics lessons from site updates. The lessons will be moved to a new webpage and given better organization and search capabilities. I also want to improve the lessons with a healthy dose of interactive Javascript so that learners can play with some simple models rather than just read text on the page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stay tuned for more updates!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 17 Jul 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>/cupcake%20physics/2017/07/17/restructuring-the-site.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">/cupcake%20physics/2017/07/17/restructuring-the-site.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Green's Function for the Two-Dimensional, Radial Laplacian</title>
				<description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.cupcakephysics.com/math%20methods/2016/11/01/greens-function-for-the-three-dimensional-radial-laplacian.html&quot;&gt;previous blog post&lt;/a&gt; I derived the Green’s function for the three-dimensional, radial Laplacian in spherical coordinates. That post showed how the actual derivation of the Green’s function was relatively straightforward, but the verification of the answer was much more involved. At the end of the post, I commented on how many textbooks simplify the expression for the Green’s function, ignoring the limiting behavior around the origin (\(r = 0\)).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided to follow up that post with a similar derivation for the two-dimensional, radial Laplacian. The derivations are almost identical - in fact, throughout this post, I will refer to the spherical Laplacian in a few places. You might want to read over the previous blog post before tackling this one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;derivation-of-the-greens-function&quot;&gt;Derivation of the Green’s Function&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider Poisson’s equation in &lt;a href=&quot;http://mathworld.wolfram.com/PolarCoordinates.html&quot;&gt;polar coordinates&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{equation}
\nabla^2 \psi = f
\end{equation}\]

&lt;p&gt;We can expand the Laplacian in terms of the \((r,\theta)\) coordinate system. I looked up the full Laplacian on &lt;a href=&quot;http://mathworld.wolfram.com/Laplacian.html&quot;&gt;Wolfram Mathworld&lt;/a&gt; (i.e. cylindrical coordinates without the z-component).&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{equation}
\frac{1}{r} \frac{\partial}{\partial r} \left ( r \frac{\partial \psi}{\partial r} \right ) + \frac{1}{r^2} \frac{\partial^2 \psi}{\partial \theta^2} = f
\end{equation}\]

&lt;p&gt;Some textbooks write the equation in a slightly different form; they expand the derivatives with respect to \(r\), yielding:&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{equation}
\frac{\partial^2 \psi}{\partial r^2} + \frac{1}{r} \frac{\partial \psi}{\partial r} + \frac{1}{r^2} \frac{\partial^2 \psi}{\partial \theta^2} = f
\end{equation}\]

&lt;p&gt;In this derivation, I am going to keep the original form of the Laplacian because it will make it easier to use integration by parts. We are only interested in the radial Green’s function here, so we can immediately simplify the expression to include only radial terms.&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{equation}
\frac{1}{r} \frac{\partial}{\partial r} \left ( r \frac{\partial \psi}{\partial r} \right ) = f
\end{equation}\]

&lt;p&gt;We are looking for a Green’s function \(G\) that satisfies:&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{equation}
\nabla^2 G = \frac{1}{r} \frac{d}{dr} \left ( r \frac{dG}{dr} \right ) = \delta(r)
\end{equation}\]

&lt;p&gt;Let’s point something out right off the bat. In the previous blog post, I set the Green’s function equal to \(4\pi \delta(r)\) wheras here, I set it equal to \(\delta(r)\) without the constant. Why is that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s because physicists love to mix all sorts of conventions and confuse people :P&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traditionally, mathematicians use \(\delta(r)\) in all cases. However, it is convenient to use \(4\pi\delta(r)\) for the derivation of the three-dimensional Green’s function for the Laplacian in spherical coordinates for a number of reasons. The final ouput is simple (no constants aside from a negative sign), the constant describes the solid angle of a sphere, and the answer aligns with &lt;a href=&quot;http://physics.stackexchange.com/questions/1673/coulomb-force-in-si-and-cgs&quot;&gt;CGS units in electromagnetism&lt;/a&gt;. However, I have not come across any sources where the 2D Green’s function is set to \(2\pi\delta(r)\). Thus, sticking with tradition, I will use \(\delta(r)\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If this change of notation rubs you the wrong way, you can go back to my previous blog post and re-derive the Green’s function using \(\delta(r)\) without the constant of \(4\pi\). Your answer will (unsurprisingly) be \(G = -1/(4\pi r)\) rather than \(G = -1/r\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s integrate both sides of the expression above with respect to \(r\). This will eliminate the Dirac delta function in the expression.&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{equation}
\int \frac{1}{r} \frac{d}{dr} \left ( r \frac{dG}{dr} \right ) dr = \int \delta(r) dr
\end{equation}\]

\[\begin{equation}
\int \frac{1}{r} \frac{d}{dr} \left ( r \frac{dG}{dr} \right ) dr = 1
\end{equation}\]

&lt;p&gt;Whenever we see derivatives within an integral, there is a chance that the integral might be simplified by integration by parts. It turns out that integration by parts works splendidly in this case.&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{equation}
u = \frac{1}{r} \Rightarrow du = -\frac{1}{r^2} dr
\end{equation}\]

\[\begin{equation}
dv = \frac{d}{dr} \left [ r \frac{dG}{dr} \right ] dr \Rightarrow v = r \frac{dG}{dr}
\end{equation}\]

&lt;p&gt;The expression becomes:&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{equation}
\left ( \frac{1}{r} \right ) \left ( r \frac{dG}{dr} \right ) - \int \left ( r \frac{dG}{dr} \right ) \left ( -\frac{1}{r^2} dr \right ) = 1
\end{equation}\]

\[\begin{equation}
\frac{dG}{dr} + \int \frac{1}{r} \frac{dG}{dr} dr = 1
\end{equation}\]

&lt;p&gt;Similar to the radial Laplacian in spherical coordinates, we can use integration by parts a second time to simplify the integral in the expression above.&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{equation}
u = \frac{1}{r} \Rightarrow du = -\frac{1}{r^2} dr
\end{equation}\]

\[\begin{equation}
dv = \frac{dG}{dr} dr \Rightarrow v = G
\end{equation}\]

&lt;p&gt;We expand the expression using integration by parts once again.&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{equation}
\frac{dG}{dr} + \left [ \left (\frac{1}{r} \right ) \left ( G \right ) - \int G \left ( -\frac{1}{r^2} dr\right ) \right ] = 1
\end{equation}\]

\[\begin{equation}
\frac{dG}{dr} + \frac{G}{r} + \int \frac{G}{r^2} dr = 1
\end{equation}\]

&lt;p&gt;It is generally preferable to work with differential equations rather than integral equations. Thus, on each side of the expression above, we can take the derivative with respect to \(r\); this will eliminate the integral in the expression. Remember that \(G\) is a function of \(r\), so we have to use the quotient rule on the \(G/r\) term.&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{equation}
\frac{d^2 G}{dr^2} + \left ( \frac{1}{r} \frac{dG}{dr} - \frac{G}{r^2} \right ) + \frac{G}{r^2} = 0
\end{equation}\]

\[\begin{equation}
\frac{d^2 G}{dr^2} + \frac{1}{r} \frac{dG}{dr} = 0
\end{equation}\]

&lt;p&gt;Similar to the case of the radial, spherical Laplacian, we have simplified the expression for \(G\) into a straightforward, differential equation. I am going to guess and check the solution \(G = A ln \vert r \vert + B\) where \(A\) and \(B\) are some constants.&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{align}
\frac{d^2 G}{dr^2} + \frac{1}{r}\frac{dG}{dr} &amp;amp;=\\
\frac{d^2}{dr^2} \left [ A ln \vert r \vert + B \right ] + \frac{1}{r}\frac{d}{dr} \left [ A ln \vert r \vert + B \right ] &amp;amp;=\\
-\frac{A}{r^2} + \frac{1}{r} \left ( \frac{A}{r} \right ) &amp;amp;=\\
-\frac{A}{r^2} + \frac{A}{r^2} &amp;amp;= 0
\end{align}\]

&lt;p&gt;Thus, we see that the solution \(G = A ln \vert r \vert + B\) solves the differential equation. Notice how \(B\) is simply an additive constant in the expression. We usually set this constant equal to zero in order to obtain the fundamental solution of the differential equation. Thus, we will use the function \(G = A ln \vert r \vert\) for the remainder of this post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;checking-the-solution&quot;&gt;Checking the Solution&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like the derivation in the previous blog post, we need to check that our solution makes sense. And like the previous blog post, we run into a small problem.&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{align}
\nabla^2 G &amp;amp;= \frac{1}{r} \frac{d}{dr} \left [ r \frac{d}{dr} \left ( A ln \vert r \vert \right ) \right ]\\
&amp;amp;= \frac{1}{r} \frac{d}{dr} \left [ r \left ( \frac{A}{r} \right ) \right ]\\
&amp;amp;= \frac{1}{r} \frac{d}{dr} \left [ A \right ]\\
&amp;amp;= 0
\end{align}\]

&lt;p&gt;Zero is not our expected output - we were expecting a Dirac delta function. The reason that we are not getting the expected output is that the domain of the solution does not include the origin \(r = 0\) (we divided by \(r\) throughout the derivation). We need to analyze the solution in the limiting case of \(r \rightarrow 0\). The strategy is identical to the previous blog post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Define a function \(\Phi_\epsilon\) where:&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{equation}
\Phi_\epsilon = A ln \vert r + \epsilon \vert
\end{equation}\]

&lt;p&gt;As \(\epsilon\) approaches zero, \(\Phi_\epsilon\) approaches the Green’s function \(G\). Let’s plug the expression \(\Phi_\epsilon\) into the Laplacian and simplify.&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{align}
\nabla^2 \Phi_\epsilon &amp;amp;= \frac{1}{r} \frac{d}{dr} \left [ r \frac{d}{dr} \left ( A ln \vert r + \epsilon \vert \right ) \right ]\\
&amp;amp;= \frac{1}{r} \frac{d}{dr} \left [ r \left ( \frac{A}{r+\epsilon} \right ) \right ]\\
&amp;amp;= \frac{1}{r} \frac{d}{dr} \left [ \frac{A r}{r+\epsilon} \right ]\\
&amp;amp;= \frac{1}{r} \left [ \frac{A}{r+\epsilon} - \frac{Ar}{(r+\epsilon)^2}\right ]\\
&amp;amp;= \frac{1}{r} \left [ \frac{A(r + \epsilon)}{(r+\epsilon)^2} - \frac{Ar}{(r+\epsilon)^2}\right ]\\
&amp;amp;= \frac{1}{r} \left [ \frac{Ar + A\epsilon - Ar}{(r+\epsilon)^2} \right ]\\
&amp;amp;= \frac{1}{r} \left [ \frac{A\epsilon}{(r+\epsilon)^2} \right ]\\
&amp;amp;= \frac{A\epsilon}{r(r+\epsilon)^2}
\end{align}\]

&lt;p&gt;Remember that by the definition of a Green’s function, the Laplacian of \(G\) (or more correctly, the Laplacian of the limiting case of \(\Phi_\epsilon\)), will yield \(\delta(r)\). If that is true, I should be able to integrate \(\nabla^2 \Phi_\epsilon\) over all space and get one. Let’s try doing just that:&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{align}
\int \nabla^2 \Phi_\epsilon dA &amp;amp;= \int_0^R \int_0^{2\pi} \frac{A\epsilon}{r(r+\epsilon)^2} r dr d\theta\\
&amp;amp;= 2\pi \int_0^R \frac{A\epsilon}{r(r+\epsilon)^2} r dr\\
&amp;amp;= 2\pi A\epsilon \int_0^R \frac{1}{(r+\epsilon)^2} dr\\
&amp;amp;= 2\pi A\epsilon \left [ - \frac{1}{r+\epsilon} \right ]_0^R\\
&amp;amp;= - 2\pi A\epsilon \left [ \frac{1}{R+\epsilon} - \frac{1}{\epsilon} \right ]\\
&amp;amp;= - 2\pi A\epsilon \left [ -\frac{R}{\epsilon(R+\epsilon)} \right ]\\
&amp;amp;=  \frac{2\pi A\epsilon R}{\epsilon(R+\epsilon)}\\
&amp;amp;=  \frac{2\pi A R}{R+\epsilon}
\end{align}\]

&lt;p&gt;If we are going to integrate over all space, we need to take the limit of this expression as \(R \rightarrow \infty\). Once again, we turn to L’Hopital’s rule.&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{align}
\lim_{R \rightarrow \infty} \int \nabla^2 \Phi_\epsilon dA &amp;amp;= \lim_{R \rightarrow \infty} \frac{2\pi A R}{R+\epsilon}\\
&amp;amp;= \lim_{R \rightarrow \infty} 2\pi A\\
&amp;amp;= 2 \pi A
\end{align}\]

&lt;p&gt;When \(A = 1/(2\pi)\), the Laplacian of \(\Phi_\epsilon\) satisfies the condition that the integral must equal one. Finally, let’s verify that the Laplacian of \(\Phi_\epsilon\) is actually a Dirac delta function. We will define one final function, \(f_\epsilon(r)\):&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{equation}
f_\epsilon (r) = \frac{1}{2 \pi A} \nabla^2 \Phi_\epsilon (r) = \frac{1}{2\pi A} \frac{A\epsilon}{r(r+\epsilon)^2} = \frac{1}{2\pi} \frac{\epsilon}{r(r+\epsilon)^2}
\end{equation}\]

&lt;p&gt;What is the value of this function in the limit of \(\epsilon \rightarrow 0\)? If \(r\) is non-zero, the limit is very simple:&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{equation}
\lim_{\epsilon \rightarrow 0} f_\epsilon (r) = \lim_{\epsilon \rightarrow 0} \frac{1}{2\pi} \frac{0}{r^3} = 0
\end{equation}\]

&lt;p&gt;However, if \(r\) is equal to zero, we need to use L’Hopital’s rule to simplify the expression.&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{equation}
\lim_{\epsilon \rightarrow 0} f_\epsilon (r) = \lim_{\epsilon \rightarrow 0} \frac{1}{2\pi} \frac{1}{2r(r+\epsilon)} = \frac{1}{2\pi} \frac{1}{2r(r)} = \frac{1}{ 4 \pi r^2}
\end{equation}\]

&lt;p&gt;This becomes infinitely large when \(r = 0\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-final-solution&quot;&gt;The Final Solution&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can now tie everything together in a similar method as the previous post. In the limit of \(\epsilon \rightarrow 0\), the function \(f_\epsilon(r)\) is infinitely large at the origin and zero everywhere else. Thus, \(f_\epsilon(r)\) is a Dirac delta function \(\delta(r)\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The function \(f_\epsilon(r)\) is equal to the Laplacian of \(\Phi_\epsilon\) (remember that the constant \((2 \pi A)^{-1}\) is equal to one since \(A=(2\pi)^{-1}\)). This means that in the limit as \(\epsilon \rightarrow 0\), the function \(\nabla^2\Phi_\epsilon\) is equal to a Dirac delta function.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, the limiting case of \(\Phi_\epsilon\) as \(\epsilon \rightarrow 0\) is equal to the Green’s function \(G = A ln \vert r \vert = (2\pi)^{-1} ln \vert r \vert\). Thus, the Laplacian of the Green’s function is a Dirac delta function. Just what we needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until next time!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Sat, 12 Nov 2016 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
				<link>/math%20methods/2016/11/12/greens-function-for-the-two-dimensional-radial-laplacian.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">/math%20methods/2016/11/12/greens-function-for-the-two-dimensional-radial-laplacian.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Green's Function for the Three-Dimensional, Radial Laplacian</title>
				<description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Laplace operator or Laplacian (\(\nabla^2\)) appears in a variety of differential equations that describe physical phenomena; topics include gravitational potential, diffusion, electromagnetic fields, quantum mechanics, and many others. All students of physics come across Poisson’s equation since it is one of the simplest, inhomogeneous differential equations involving the Laplacian.&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{equation}
\nabla^2 \psi = f
\end{equation}\]

&lt;p&gt;In the expression above, \(\nabla^2\) is the Laplacian, \(f\) is a known function, and \(\psi\) is a function that we must solve for. Techniques like &lt;a href=&quot;http://mathworld.wolfram.com/SeparationofVariables.html&quot;&gt;separation of variables&lt;/a&gt; are commonly used to solve for \(\phi\) when \(f\) is separable, but solving for \(\psi\) can become very complicated in more sophisticated cases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Green’s functions are a staple in upper-level physics because they can be used to simplify or solve more complicated expressions (like when \(f\) is not separable). In this post, we will derive the Green’s function for the three-dimensional Laplacian in spherical coordinates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;derivation-of-the-greens-function&quot;&gt;Derivation of the Green’s Function&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider Poisson’s equation in spherical coordinates.&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{equation}
\nabla^2 \psi = f
\end{equation}\]

&lt;p&gt;We can expand the Laplacian in terms of the \((r,\theta,\phi)\) coordinate system. I looked up the full Laplacian on &lt;a href=&quot;http://mathworld.wolfram.com/Laplacian.html&quot;&gt;Wolfram Mathworld&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{equation}
\left [ \frac{1}{r^2} \frac{\partial}{\partial r} \left ( r^2 \frac{\partial \psi}{\partial r} \right ) + \frac{1}{r^2 sin^2 \phi} \frac{\partial^2 \psi}{\partial \theta^2} + \frac{1}{r^2 sin\phi} \frac{\partial}{\partial \phi} \left ( sin\phi \frac{\partial \psi}{\partial \phi} \right ) \right ] = f
\end{equation}\]

&lt;p&gt;Since we are only interested in the radial Green’s function, we can immediately simplify the expression above to include only radial terms. Anything with a \(\theta\) or \(\phi\) gets canceled:&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{equation}
\frac{1}{r^2} \frac{\partial}{\partial r} \left ( r^2 \frac{\partial \psi}{\partial r} \right ) = f
\end{equation}\]

&lt;p&gt;We want to find the Green’s function for the Laplace operator. In other words, we are looking for a function \(G\) that satisfies:&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{equation}
\nabla^2 G = 4\pi \delta(r)
\end{equation}\]

&lt;p&gt;Using the expression for the Laplacian from above, we get:&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{equation}
\frac{1}{r^2} \frac{d}{dr} \left ( r^2 \frac{dG}{dr} \right ) = 4\pi \delta(r)
\end{equation}\]

&lt;p&gt;Since the right-hand side of the equation contains a Dirac delta function, it seems natural to integrate both sides with respect to \(r\). The expression becomes:&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{equation}
\int \frac{1}{r^2} \frac{d}{dr} \left ( r^2 \frac{dG}{dr} \right ) dr = \int 4\pi \delta(r) dr
\end{equation}\]

\[\begin{equation}
\int \frac{1}{r^2} \frac{d}{dr} \left ( r^2 \frac{dG}{dr} \right ) dr = 4\pi
\end{equation}\]

&lt;p&gt;The derivatives within the integral suggest that this expression might be simplified by integration by parts. Let’s give it a shot:&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{equation}
u = \frac{1}{r^2} \Rightarrow du = -\frac{2}{r^3} dr
\end{equation}\]

\[\begin{equation}
dv = \frac{d}{dr} \left [ r^2 \frac{dG}{dr} \right ] dr \Rightarrow v = r^2 \frac{dG}{dr}
\end{equation}\]

&lt;p&gt;Thus, the expression becomes:&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{equation}
\left ( \frac{1}{r^2} \right ) \left ( r^2 \frac{dG}{dr} \right ) - \int \left ( r^2 \frac{dG}{dr} \right ) \left ( -\frac{2}{r^3} dr \right ) = 4\pi
\end{equation}\]

\[\begin{equation}
\frac{dG}{dr} + 2 \int \frac{1}{r} \frac{dG}{dr} dr = 4\pi
\end{equation}\]

&lt;p&gt;This integral looks a little simpler, but we can do better! We can use integration by parts a second time to simplify it even further.&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{equation}
u = \frac{1}{r} \Rightarrow du = -\frac{1}{r^2} dr
\end{equation}\]

\[\begin{equation}
dv = \frac{dG}{dr} dr \Rightarrow v = G
\end{equation}\]

&lt;p&gt;We expand the expression once again.&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{equation}
\frac{dG}{dr} + 2 \left [ \left (\frac{1}{r} \right ) \left ( G \right ) - \int G \left ( -\frac{1}{r^2} dr\right ) \right ] = 4\pi
\end{equation}\]

\[\begin{equation}
\frac{dG}{dr} + 2 \left [ \frac{G}{r} + \int \frac{G}{r^2} dr \right ] = 4\pi
\end{equation}\]

\[\begin{equation}
\frac{dG}{dr} + \frac{2G}{r} + 2 \int \frac{G}{r^2} dr = 4\pi
\end{equation}\]

&lt;p&gt;Dealing with derivatives is usually easier than dealing with integral equations. Thus, we should take the derivative with respect to \(r\) on each side in order to eliminate the integral. Note that \(G\) is a function of \(r\), so we have to use the quotient rule on the \(2G/r\) term. This causes a couple of terms to cancel out nicely.&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{equation}
\frac{d^2 G}{dr^2} + \left ( \frac{2}{r} \frac{dG}{dr} - \frac{2G}{r^2} \right ) + \frac{2G}{r^2} = 0
\end{equation}\]

\[\begin{equation}
\frac{d^2 G}{dr^2} + \frac{2}{r} \frac{dG}{dr} = 0
\end{equation}\]

&lt;p&gt;Hooray! We turned Poisson’s equation for \(G\) into a slightly less difficult to solve differential equation for \(G\)!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;solving-the-second-differential-equation&quot;&gt;Solving the Second Differential Equation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can solve this new differential equation in a number of ways. I am going to use a tried and true method of analysis - guess and check! I am going to guess a solution of \(G = A/r\) since that seems to fit pretty well. The variable A is some constant.&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{align}
\frac{d^2 G}{dr^2} + \frac{2}{r}\frac{dG}{dr} &amp;amp;=\\
\frac{d^2}{dr^2} \left [ \frac{A}{r} \right ] + \frac{2}{r}\frac{d}{dr} \left [ \frac{A}{r} \right ] &amp;amp;=\\
\frac{2A}{r^3} + \frac{2}{r} \left ( -\frac{A}{r^2} \right ) &amp;amp;=\\
\frac{2A}{r^3} - \frac{2A}{r^3} &amp;amp;= 0
\end{align}\]

&lt;p&gt;Thus, we see that \(G = A/r\) is the solution for our differential equation above. Or is it…?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Update (November 12, 2016): Technically, the solution of this differential equation is \(G = A/r + B\) where both \(A\) and \(B\) are constants. However, we usually set \(B\) equal to zero in order to obtain the so-called fundamental solution. The fundamental solution ignores scaling by a constant and instead looks at the properties of how \(G\) changes with \(r\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;checking-the-solution&quot;&gt;Checking the Solution&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have a bit of a problem. Suppose I plug \(G = A/r\) back into the Laplacian. Let’s see what happens:&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{align}
\nabla^2 G &amp;amp;= \frac{1}{r^2} \frac{d}{dr} \left [ r^2 \frac{d}{dr} \left ( \frac{A}{r} \right ) \right ]\\
&amp;amp;= \frac{1}{r^2} \frac{d}{dr} \left [ r^2 \left ( -\frac{A}{r^2} \right ) \right ]\\
&amp;amp;= \frac{1}{r^2} \frac{d}{dr} \left [ -A \right ]\\
&amp;amp;= 0
\end{align}\]

&lt;p&gt;Technically speaking, that is not our expected output. We were expecting a Dirac delta function and instead got zero. So what gives?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember, we divided by \(r\) throughout the derivation, so the domain of the solution cannot include the origin \(r = 0\). We can, however, analyze the solution in the limiting case. Suppose we define a function \(\Phi_\epsilon\) where:&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{equation}
\Phi_\epsilon = \frac{A}{r + \epsilon}
\end{equation}\]

&lt;p&gt;As \(\epsilon\) approaches zero, \(\Phi_\epsilon\) approaches the Green’s function \(G\). Let’s plug the expression \(\Phi_\epsilon\) into the Laplacian and turn the crank.&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{align}
\nabla^2 \Phi_\epsilon &amp;amp;= \frac{1}{r^2} \frac{d}{dr} \left [ r^2 \frac{d}{dr} \left ( \frac{A}{r + \epsilon} \right ) \right ]\\
&amp;amp;= \frac{1}{r^2} \frac{d}{dr} \left [ r^2 \left ( -\frac{A}{(r+\epsilon)^2} \right ) \right ]\\
&amp;amp;= \frac{1}{r^2} \frac{d}{dr} \left [ -\frac{A r^2}{(r+\epsilon)^2} \right ]\\
&amp;amp;= \frac{1}{r^2} \left [ -\frac{2A\epsilon r}{(r+\epsilon)^3} \right ]\\
&amp;amp;= -\frac{2A\epsilon}{r(r+\epsilon)^3}
\end{align}\]

&lt;p&gt;Ok, we are getting some expression with \(r\)’s and \(\epsilon\)’s. What does it mean?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember, I claimed that the Laplacian of \(G\) (or more correctly, the Laplacian of the limiting case of \(\Phi_\epsilon\)), will yield \(4 \pi \delta(r)\). If that is true, I should be able to integrate \(\nabla^2 \Phi_\epsilon\) over all space and get \(4\pi\). Let’s try doing just that:&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{align}
\int \nabla^2 \Phi_\epsilon dV &amp;amp;= - \int_0^R \int_0^{2\pi} \int_0^\pi \frac{2A\epsilon}{r(r+\epsilon)^3} r^2 sin\theta dr d\theta d\phi\\
&amp;amp;= - 4\pi \int_0^R \frac{2A\epsilon r}{(r+\epsilon)^3} dr\\
&amp;amp;= - 4\pi A \left [ \frac{r(2\epsilon + r)}{(r+\epsilon)^2} \right ]_0^R\\
&amp;amp;= - 4\pi A \left [ \frac{R(2\epsilon + R)}{(R + \epsilon)^2} \right ]\\
&amp;amp;= - 4\pi A \left [ \frac{R^2 + 2\epsilon R}{R^2 + 2\epsilon R + \epsilon^2} \right ]\\
\end{align}\]

&lt;p&gt;If we are going to integrate over all space, we need to take the limit of this expression as \(R \rightarrow \infty\). This is a job for L’Hopital’s rule!&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{align}
\lim_{R \rightarrow \infty} \int \nabla^2 \Phi_\epsilon dV &amp;amp;= \lim_{R \rightarrow \infty} - 4\pi A \left [ \frac{R^2 + 2\epsilon R}{R^2 + 2\epsilon R + \epsilon^2} \right ]\\
&amp;amp;= \lim_{R \rightarrow \infty} - 4\pi A \left [ \frac{2R + 2\epsilon}{2R + 2\epsilon} \right ] = - 4\pi A
\end{align}\]

&lt;p&gt;It seems that when \(A = -1\), the Laplacian of \(\Phi_\epsilon\) satisfies our conditions. Let’s define one last function \(f_\epsilon(r)\) to simplify the expression. I promise we are in the home stretch!&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{equation}
f_\epsilon (r) = \frac{1}{4 \pi A} \nabla^2 \Phi_\epsilon (r) = -\frac{1}{4\pi} \nabla^2 \Phi_\epsilon (r) = \frac{\epsilon}{2\pi r (r+\epsilon)^3}
\end{equation}\]

&lt;p&gt;We should take a good, long look at this equation in the limit of \(\epsilon \rightarrow 0\). If \(r\) is non-zero, the limit is very simple:&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{equation}
\lim_{\epsilon \rightarrow 0} f_\epsilon (r) = \lim_{\epsilon \rightarrow 0} \frac{\epsilon}{2\pi r (r+\epsilon)^3} = \frac{0}{2\pi r (r)^3} = 0
\end{equation}\]

&lt;p&gt;If \(r\) is equal to zero, we need to use L’Hopital’s rule to simplify the expression.&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{equation}
\lim_{\epsilon \rightarrow 0} f_\epsilon (r) = \lim_{\epsilon \rightarrow 0} \frac{\epsilon}{2\pi r (r+\epsilon)^3} = \lim_{\epsilon \rightarrow 0} \frac{1}{6 \pi r(r + \epsilon)^2} = \frac{1}{6 \pi r^3}
\end{equation}\]

&lt;p&gt;This becomes infinitely large when \(r = 0\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;putting-it-all-together&quot;&gt;Putting It All Together&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s tie everything together. In the limiting case of \(\epsilon \rightarrow 0\), the function \(f_\epsilon(r)\) is infinitely large at the origin and zero everywhere else. This means that \(f_\epsilon(r)\) is a Dirac delta function \(\delta(r)\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The function \(f_\epsilon(r)\) is equal to the Laplacian of \(\Phi_\epsilon\), multiplied by a constant. Thus, in the limit as \(\epsilon \rightarrow 0\), the function \(\nabla^2\Phi_\epsilon\) is equal to a Dirac delta function (times a constant).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But remember that the limiting case of \(\Phi_\epsilon\) as \(\epsilon \rightarrow 0\) is equivalent to the Green’s function \(G = A/r = -1/r\). Thus, the Laplacian of the Green’s function is a Dirac delta function times the constant \(4\pi\). This is exactly what we set out to prove in the first place! Woot!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One final thought. You often see the following expression written out in textbooks:&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{equation}
\nabla^2 \left ( \frac{1}{r} \right ) = -4\pi \delta(r)
\end{equation}\]

&lt;p&gt;Technically, this is not entirely correct because \(1/r\) is undefined at the origin. It should really be written as the following.&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{equation}
\lim_{\epsilon \rightarrow 0} \left [ \nabla^2 \left ( \frac{1}{r + \epsilon} \right ) \right ] = -4\pi \delta(r)
\end{equation}\]

&lt;p&gt;This comes directly from the analysis above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until next time!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Tue, 01 Nov 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>/math%20methods/2016/11/01/greens-function-for-the-three-dimensional-radial-laplacian.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">/math%20methods/2016/11/01/greens-function-for-the-three-dimensional-radial-laplacian.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Short Break</title>
				<description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-short-break&quot;&gt;A Short Break&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am finishing up my Ph.D. in physics over the next few months, so I am going to have to take a small break from blogging in order to analyze my data and write my thesis. You might have already noticed that I haven’t written a new post in awhile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t despair! Cupcake Physics is still going to be active on social media. And the Cupcake Physics blog will be back in full force this September, followed shortly by the main Cupcake Physics site! Until then, please feel free to peruse any existing content on the blog.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Wed, 16 Mar 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
				<link>/cupcake%20physics/2016/03/16/short-break.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">/cupcake%20physics/2016/03/16/short-break.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Plasma Oscillations</title>
				<description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have probably heard that free electrons within a conductor are able to move about the crystal. This makes it possible for conductors to carry currents and thermal energy very efficiently. There are plenty of examples of this in real life. Electrical wires are made out of copper, not wood. The heat sink in your computer is made out of aluminum or copper, not plastic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chemists often use the term &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metallic_bonding&quot;&gt;metallic bond&lt;/a&gt; to describe how shared electrons between metallic nuclei can hold metallic atoms together. Physicists use the terms electron liquid or electron gas to describe the free electrons in a metal. An electron liquid includes all of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Coulomb%27s_law&quot;&gt;Coulomb interactions&lt;/a&gt; between the electrons while an electron gas (also called a free electron gas or a free Fermi gas) does not include these interactions. For now, we are going to focus on the free electron gas - the electrons do not interact with each other and the positive nuceli in the background are assumed to create a nearly uniform potential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we were to apply an external electric field to a uniform conductor, the electrons should feel a force in the appropriate direction. If we were to apply an oscillating external electric field to a uniform conductor, the electrons will wiggle with the electric field. These plasma oscillations (sometimes called Langmuir waves after their discoverer, Irving Langmuir) have some very interesting properties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-equation-of-motion&quot;&gt;The Equation of Motion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suppose I want to analyze the motion of an electron in an &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Isotropy&quot;&gt;isotropic&lt;/a&gt; conductor under an external, oscillating, electric field. We will use the free Fermi gas approximation, so a random electron is only affected by:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Any damping forces it feels while moving around in the crystal (approximated as linear damping).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Any binding forces it feels to atoms in the crystal (approximated as a restoring force like that of a spring).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The external electric field that we apply to the conductor (no approximation necessary).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let \(\vec{r}(t)\) denote the position of our electron as a function of time and \(\vec{E}(t)\) denote the external electric field as a function of time. We can use Newton’s second law to determine the equation of motion for the electron in the conductor.&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{equation}
\sum \vec{F}(t) = m\vec{a}(t)
\end{equation}\]

\[\begin{equation}
-m\Gamma \vec{v}(t) - m\Omega^2 \vec{r}(t) + e \vec{E}(t) = m\vec{a}(t)
\end{equation}\]

\[\begin{equation}
-m\Gamma \frac{d \vec{r}(t)}{dt} - m\Omega^2 \vec{r}(t) + e \vec{E}(t) = m\frac{d^2 \vec{r}(t)}{dt^2}
\end{equation}\]

\[\begin{equation}
m\frac{d^2 \vec{r}(t)}{dt^2} + m\Gamma \frac{d \vec{r}(t)}{dt} + m\Omega^2 \vec{r}(t) = e \vec{E}(t)
\end{equation}\]

&lt;p&gt;In the equations above, the electron has mass m and charge e. It is bound to a given atom with a spring-like force with spring constant \(m\Omega^2\). As it moves through the crystal, it feels a retarding frictional force with coefficient \(m\Gamma\). These approximations may not seem like they would lead to correct answers, but they are surprisingly accurate!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have already mentioned that the electrons within a conductor are free to move about the crystal. Thus, \(\Omega \rightarrow 0\), and we can recast the equation above in terms of the electron velocity.&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{equation}
m\frac{d^2 \vec{r}(t)}{dt^2} + m\Gamma \frac{d \vec{r}(t)}{dt} = e \vec{E}(t)
\end{equation}\]

\[\begin{equation}
\frac{d^2 \vec{r}(t)}{dt^2} + \Gamma \frac{d \vec{r}(t)}{dt} = \frac{e}{m} \vec{E}(t)
\end{equation}\]

\[\begin{equation}
\frac{d \vec{v}(t)}{dt} + \Gamma \vec{v}(t) = \frac{e}{m} \vec{E}(t)
\end{equation}\]

&lt;p&gt;We know that the electron is going to oscillate as a function of time due to the external electric field. Suppose the electric field is given by \(\vec{E}(t) = \vec{E}e^{-i\omega t}\). Then, the velocity of the electron is given by \(\vec{v}(t) = \vec{v} e^{-i\omega t}\) where \(\vec{v}\) is some velocity vector and \(\omega\) is the frequency of our oscillating electric field. In other words, we are solving this differential equation by guessing the solution for \(\vec{v}(t)\).&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{equation}
\frac{d}{dt} \left [ \vec{v} e^{-i\omega t} \right ] + \Gamma \vec{v}e^{-i\omega t} = \frac{e}{m} \vec{E} e^{-i\omega t}
\end{equation}\]

\[\begin{equation}
\vec{v} \frac{d}{dt} e^{-i\omega t} + \Gamma \vec{v}e^{-i\omega t} = \frac{e}{m} \vec{E} e^{-i\omega t}
\end{equation}\]

\[\begin{equation}
-i\omega \vec{v} e^{-i\omega t} + \Gamma \vec{v}e^{-i\omega t} = \frac{e}{m} \vec{E} e^{-i\omega t}
\end{equation}\]

\[\begin{equation}
-i\omega \vec{v} + \Gamma \vec{v} = \frac{e}{m} \vec{E}
\end{equation}\]

&lt;p&gt;Solving for \(\vec{v}\) gives:&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{equation}
\left ( -i\omega + \Gamma \right ) \vec{v} = \frac{e}{m} \vec{E}
\end{equation}\]

\[\begin{equation}
\vec{v} = \frac{e \vec{E}}{m \left ( -i\omega + \Gamma \right )}
\end{equation}\]

&lt;p&gt;What is this answer telling us? Notice how the direction of \(\vec{v}\) depends only on the direction of \(\vec{E}\). Our electron oscillations line up with the polarization of the external electric field (as we might guess). Let’s use this result to calculate the conductivity of the metal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;conductivity&quot;&gt;Conductivity&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ohm’s law defines the electrical conductivity of a system as:&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{equation}
\vec{J}(t) = \sigma \vec{E}(t)
\end{equation}\]

&lt;p&gt;where \(\vec{J}(t)\) is the time-dependent current density, \(\sigma\) is the conductivity, and \(\vec{E}(t)\) is the time-dependent electric field acting on the system. With a few steps of algebra, you can turn this expression back into good old \(V=IR\) (that will be another post though).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since we are dealing with an angular frequency \(\omega\), it might be easier to analyze Ohm’s law in the frequency domain rather than the time domain. Just like we did above, let \(\vec{E}(t) = \vec{E}e^{-i\omega t}\) and \(\vec{J}(t) = \vec{J}e^{-i\omega t}\). Taking the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wolframalpha.com/input/?i=fourier+transform+exp%28-i*w*t%29&quot;&gt;Fourier transform of each side&lt;/a&gt; yields:&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{equation}
F[\vec{J}(t)] = \sqrt{2\pi} \vec{J}
\end{equation}\]

\[\begin{equation}
F[\vec{E}(t)] = \sqrt{2\pi} \vec{E}
\end{equation}\]

\[\begin{equation}
\vec{J} = \sigma \vec{E}
\end{equation}\]

&lt;p&gt;We can express \(\vec{J}\) in terms of the velocity and the carrier density of the material (n):&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{equation}
\vec{J} = ne\vec{v}
\end{equation}\]

&lt;p&gt;Substituting the expression for \(\vec{v}\) from the previous section yields:&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{equation}
\vec{J} = \frac{ne^2 \vec{E}}{m \left ( -i\omega + \Gamma \right )} =  \sigma \vec{E}
\end{equation}\]

\[\begin{equation}
\sigma = \frac{ne^2}{m} \frac{1}{ \left ( -i\omega + \Gamma \right )}
\end{equation}\]

&lt;p&gt;If we let \(\Gamma \equiv 1/\tau\) (where \(\tau\) is the mean free time of the electron), the expression becomes:&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{equation}
\sigma = \frac{ne^2 \tau}{m} \frac{1}{ \left (1 - i\omega\tau \right )} = \frac{ne^2 \tau}{m} \left ( \frac{1 + i\omega \tau}{1 + \omega^2 \tau^2} \right )
\end{equation}\]

&lt;p&gt;The conductivity can now be used to solve for the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Permittivity#Lossy_medium&quot;&gt;complex permittivity&lt;/a&gt; of the system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;complex-permittivity&quot;&gt;Complex Permittivity&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can find the complex permittivity of the conductor (in Gaussian units) according to:&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{equation}
\epsilon = \epsilon_r + \frac{4\pi i\sigma}{\omega}
\end{equation}\]

&lt;p&gt;where \(\epsilon_r\) is the relative permittivity of the specific conductor within which the oscillations are taking place. Remember, we are using \(exp(-i \omega t)\) as the oscillating term, so the complex permittivity has a plus sign rather than a minus sign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notice the imaginary number (i) in the expression for complex permittivity. The imaginary part of \(\sigma\) contributes to the real part of \(\epsilon\) (an imaginary number multiplied by an imaginary number is real) while the real part of \(\sigma\) contributes to the imaginary part of \(\epsilon\) (a real number multiplied by an imagninary number is imaginary). In other words, the real part of \(\sigma\) contributes to the loss in the system while the imaginary part of \(\sigma\) contributes to the permittivity of the system.&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{align}
\epsilon &amp;amp;= \epsilon_r + \frac{4\pi i n e^2 \tau}{m \omega} \left ( \frac{1 + i\omega\tau}{1 + \omega^2\tau^2 } \right )\\
&amp;amp;= \epsilon_r + \frac{4\pi i n e^2 \tau}{m \omega} \frac{1}{1 + \omega^2\tau^2 } + \frac{4\pi i n e^2 \tau}{m \omega} \frac{i\omega \tau}{1 + \omega^2\tau^2 }\\
&amp;amp;= \epsilon_r + \frac{4\pi i n e^2 \tau}{m \omega} \frac{1}{1 + \omega^2\tau^2 } - \frac{4\pi n e^2 \tau}{m \omega} \frac{\omega \tau}{1 + \omega^2\tau^2 }\\
&amp;amp;= \epsilon_r + \frac{4\pi i n e^2 \tau}{m \omega \left ( 1 + \omega^2\tau^2 \right ) } - \frac{4\pi n e^2 \tau^2}{m \left ( 1 + \omega^2\tau^2 \right ) }
\end{align}\]

&lt;p&gt;In the limit of \(\omega\tau \gg 1\), the expression becomes:&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{align}
\epsilon &amp;amp;\approx \epsilon_r + \frac{4\pi i n e^2 \tau}{m \omega \left ( \omega^2\tau^2 \right ) } - \frac{4\pi n e^2 \tau^2}{m \left ( \omega^2\tau^2 \right ) }\\
&amp;amp;= \epsilon_r + \frac{4\pi i n e^2}{m \omega^3 \tau } - \frac{4\pi n e^2}{m \omega^2 }\\
\end{align}\]

&lt;p&gt;We technically have an expression for the complex permittivity of the system. However, physicists usually make one more simplification. Let’s look at the real part of the permittivity in the limit of \(\omega\tau \gg 1\):&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{equation}
Re[\epsilon] \approx \epsilon_r \left [ 1 - \frac{4\pi ne^2}{m \omega^2 \epsilon_r} \right ] = \epsilon_r \left [ 1 - \frac{\omega_p^2}{\omega^2} \right ]
\end{equation}\]

&lt;p&gt;where \(\omega_p = [4\pi n e^2/m\epsilon_r]^{1/2}\) is the plasma frequency of the system. You can think of the plasma frequency as the resonant frequency of electrons in the metal for small oscillations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;conclusions&quot;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We learned that an oscillating electric field incident on a conductor causes the electrons to oscillate at the same frequency. The electrons in a conductor have a resonant frequency, just like the driven mass-spring oscillator. We call it the plasma frequency of the conductor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The formula for plasma frequency is a little bit strange though. If the incident frequency of light is greater than the plasma frequency, we see that the index of refraction of the metal will be less than one since \(n = \sqrt{\epsilon}\). On first glance, this seems to violate the laws of special relativity (light in the metal is traveling faster than light in a vacuum because v = c/n). We will cover that in a future post.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 18 Jan 2016 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
				<link>/electromagnetism/2016/01/18/plasma-oscillations.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">/electromagnetism/2016/01/18/plasma-oscillations.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>An Electromagnetic Wave in a Conductor (Part 2)</title>
				<description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.cupcakephysics.com/electromagnetism/2016/01/03/an-electromagnetic-wave-in-a-conductor-part-1.html&quot;&gt;Last week&lt;/a&gt; we used Maxwell’s equations to derive an expression for the wavevector of an electromagnetic wave within a conductor. We found that the wavevector turns out to be a complex number given by:&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{equation}
\widetilde{k} = \omega \sqrt{ \mu \epsilon - \frac{i \mu \sigma}{\omega} } = \frac{\widetilde{n} \omega}{c}
\end{equation}\]

&lt;p&gt;where&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{equation}
\widetilde{n} = c \sqrt{ \mu \epsilon - \frac{i \mu \sigma}{\omega} }
\end{equation}\]

&lt;p&gt;Of course, you can solve for the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wolframalpha.com/input/?i=Real%5B+sqrt%28A+%2B+B*i%29+%5D&quot;&gt;real&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wolframalpha.com/input/?i=Imaginary%5B+sqrt%28A+%2B+B*i%29+%5D&quot;&gt;imaginary&lt;/a&gt; parts of \(\widetilde{n}\) or \(\widetilde{k}\) using a little bit of algebra. However, that doesn’t tell us what complex values actually mean. For that, we will simply look back to the formula for a plane wave of light.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-plane-wave&quot;&gt;The Plane Wave&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The electric field of a plane wave of light propagating in some material has the form:&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{equation}
\vec{E}(\vec{r}) = \vec{E}_o e^{i(\vec{k} \cdot \vec{r} + \omega t)} = \vec{E}_o e^{i\vec{k} \cdot \vec{r}} e^{i\omega t}
\end{equation}\]

&lt;p&gt;In this plane wave the wavevector, refractive index, speed of light, and frequency of the light wave are all related by a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dispersion_relation&quot;&gt;dispersion relationship&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{equation}
ck = n\omega \Rightarrow k = \frac{n\omega}{c}
\end{equation}\]

&lt;p&gt;We will assume that the propagation of light is along the z-direction, meaning that the plane wave expression reduces down to:&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{equation}
\vec{E}(z) = \vec{E}_o e^{ikz} e^{i\omega t}
\end{equation}\]

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, we will ignore the \(\omega t\) term for the time being, just so we can get a sense of the shape of the wave without worrying about the oscillations of the wave.&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{equation}
\vec{E}(z) = \vec{E}_o e^{ikz}
\end{equation}\]

&lt;p&gt;If k is a real number, then the expression above has the form of a regular, old, oscillating wave. However, if the wavevector is complex, something interesting happens. Let \(\widetilde{k}\) be complex and \(k_1\) and \(k_2\) be real numbers:&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{equation}
\widetilde{k} = k_1 + ik_2
\end{equation}\]

&lt;p&gt;Then:&lt;/p&gt;

\[\begin{align}
\vec{E}(z) &amp;amp;= \vec{E}_o e^{i\widetilde{k}z}\\
&amp;amp;= \vec{E}_o e^{i(k_1 + ik_2)z}\\
&amp;amp;= \vec{E}_o e^{ik_1z + i^2k_2z}\\
&amp;amp;= \vec{E}_o e^{ik_1z - k_2z}\\
&amp;amp;= \vec{E}_o e^{ik_1z} e^{-k_2z}\\
\end{align}\]

&lt;p&gt;The real part of \(\widetilde{k}\) (and by extension \(\widetilde{n}\)) determines the wavevector of the light in the material. The imaginary part of \(\widetilde{k}\) (and by extension \(\widetilde{n}\)) is seen in a negative exponential term. This means that the electric field decays - the light wave can only penetrate part of the way into the conductor. This is called the skin depth of the wave in the conductor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can use the interactive plot below to see how changing \(k_1\) and \(k_2\) will affect the magnitude of the electromagnetic wave as a function of z-position. The blue curve represents the real part of the electric field while the red curve represents the imaginary part. The initial magnitude of the electric field has been scaled to one, just to provide a consistent starting point for the analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div id=&quot;skin_depth&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;center&gt;
&lt;table style=&quot;table-layout: fixed; width: 560px&quot;&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;\(k_1\)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;range&quot; id=&quot;kOneSlider&quot; min=&quot;0&quot; max=&quot;80&quot; step=&quot;1&quot; value=&quot;40&quot; oninput=&quot;updateGraph();&quot; onchange=&quot;updateGraph();&quot; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;kOneReadout&quot;&gt;40.0&lt;/span&gt; \(m^{-1}\)&lt;/td&gt;
	&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;\(k_2\)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;range&quot; id=&quot;kTwoSlider&quot; min=&quot;0&quot; max=&quot;10&quot; step=&quot;0.1&quot; value=&quot;0&quot; oninput=&quot;updateGraph();&quot; onchange=&quot;updateGraph();&quot; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;kTwoReadout&quot;&gt;0.0&lt;/span&gt; \(m^{-1}\)&lt;/td&gt;
	&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;
		&lt;td colspan=&quot;3&quot;&gt;The real part of the electric field is in &lt;font color=&quot;blue&quot;&gt;BLUE&lt;/font&gt; while the imaginary part of the electric field is in &lt;font color=&quot;red&quot;&gt;RED&lt;/font&gt;.&lt;/td&gt;
	&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot; src=&quot;/assets/js/2016-01-10/skin_depth.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

</description>
				<pubDate>Sun, 10 Jan 2016 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
				<link>/electromagnetism/2016/01/10/an-electromagnetic-wave-in-a-conductor-part-2.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">/electromagnetism/2016/01/10/an-electromagnetic-wave-in-a-conductor-part-2.html</guid>
			</item>
		
	</channel>
</rss>
